Register of the William Warren Bartley miscellaneous papers
Hoover Institution Archives
William Warren Bartley miscellaneous papers
1975-1988
91022
Hoover Institution Archives
3 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 1 card file box (3.3 linear feet)
Drafts, galleys, proofs, memoranda, and correspondence related to production of the first volume of the collected works of the Austrian economist Friedrich A. von Hayek, The Fatal Conceit: The Errors of Socialism (London, 1988), edited by William W. Bartley; and sound recordings of speeches and lectures by F. A. von Hayek and others related to laissez-faire economics.
Bartley, William Warren, 1934-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Friedrich A. von Hayek papers, Hoover Institution Archives Sir Karl Raimund Popper papers, Hoover Institution Archives Gerald P. O'Driscoll correspondence with Friedrich A. von Hayek, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1934 Born, Wilkinsburg, Pennsylvania
1956 B.A. in philosophy, Harvard University
1958 A.M. in philosophy, Harvard University
1961-1964 Lecturer, Warburg Institute, University of London
1962 Ph.D, London School of Economics (studied under Karl Popper)
1965-1966 Co-director, Humanities Program, University of California, San Diego
1967-1968 Associate professor, University of Pittsburg
1969-1973 Professor and senior research associate, University of Pittsburg
1970-1989 Professor, California State University at Hayward
1973 Professor of philosophy at California State University, Hayward Author, Wittgenstein
1977 Editor, Lewis Carroll's Symbolic Logic
1978 Author, Werner Erhard, the Transformation of a Man: The Founding of est
1982 Editor, The Open Universe: An Argument for Indeterminism and Quantum Theory and the Schism in Physics: From The Postscript to the Logic of Scientific Discovery by Karl Popper
1983 Editor, Realism and the Aim of Science by Karl Popper
1985- Senior research fellow, Hoover Institution
1988 Editor, The Fatal Conceit: The Errors of Socialism by Friedrich A. von Hayek
1990 Author, Unfathomed Knowledge, Unmeasured Wealth: On Universities and the Wealth of Nations Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The William W. Bartley papers contain drafts of the first volume of the collected works of Friedrich A. von Hayek, The Fatal Conceit: The Errors of Socialism and sound recordings of speeches and lectures by F. A. von Hayek and others.
William Warren Bartley was a professor and American philosopher who edited works by Karl Popper and Friedrich A. von Hayek. He was the editor of Hayek's The Fatal Conceit, a book which discusses Hayek's view of socialism, defining the fatal conceit as the idea that "man is able to shape the world according to his wishes" (p. 27). The Fatal Conceit file contains drafts of this work and related correspondence.
The collection contains Sound recordings of economics lectures by Friedrich A. von Hayek, Ronald Coase, Roger Garrison, William Hutt, Israel Kirzner, Murry Rothbard, Gerald O'Driscoll, and other economists.
Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-1992.; Economics.; Economists.; Laissez-faire.; Liberty.; Phonotapes.
- The Fatal Conceit file, 1987-1988
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes annotated drafts and correspondence related to the production of the first volume of the collected works of Friedrich A. von Hayek, The Fatal Conceit: The Errors of Socialism. Arranged chronologically. Some dates of drafts taken from attached correspondence.
  - Bibliography and end notes, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Endnotes, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Proofs, annotated, undated (Box-folder 1: 3-5)
  - Typescripts, undated (Box-folder 1: 6-8)
  - Typescript, "original", undated (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - Typescript, 1987 August (Box-folder 2: 3-4)
  - Typescript, part 1, 1987 November (Box-folder 2: 5-6)
  - Typescript, annotated, circa 1988 January (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - Typesetting proofs, 1988 March (Box-folder 3: 3-4)
  - Typesetting proofs and inserts, American edition, 1988 March (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Typesetting proofs, British edition, 1988 March (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Proofs, 1988 June (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Letter from Gary Davis with title page, 1988 August (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Front matter and letter from Peter Sowden, 1988 September (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Sound recordings, 1975-1976, undated; 50 sound cassettes
  Contains 50 compact sound cassettes of economics lectures by F. A. von Hayek, Ronald Coase, Roger Garrison, William Hutt, Israel Kirzner, Murry Rothbard, Gerald O'Driscoll, and others. The majority of cassettes in the collection retain an original numbering system, with cassettes labeled 1 to 21 and 165 to 182, although there are some gaps within this system. Tapes labeled with these numbers are arranged in numerical order, while tapes without numbers are arranged alphabetically by speaker (or by title when the speaker cannot be identified). Titles are inscribed from labels and may not match content.
  - Liberty Audio lectures (Box 4)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010499
    Parts 01-03: 'Spontaneous Order and the Economic Point of View' by Israel Kirzner Parts 04-06: 'The Foundations of Economic Understanding' by Israel Kirzner Parts 07-09: 'Competition as a Process' Parts 10-11: 'The 'Problem' of Monopoly' by Roger Garrison Parts 12-14: 'A Perspective on Antitrust Policy' by Gerald O'Driscoll Parts 15-16: 'Externalities and the Notion of Social Cost' by Gerald O'Driscoll Parts 17-19: 'Production in a Market Economy' by Roger Garrison Parts 20-22: 'The Austrian Theory of Money and Monetary Institutions' by Gerald O'Driscoll Parts 23-25: 'The Austrian Theory of the Business Cycle' by Roger Garrison Parts 26-28: 'A Critique of Keynesianism and Monetarism' by Roger Garrison Parts 29-31: 'Consumer Sovereignty and the Market System' by Roger Garrison Parts 32-34: 'The Morality of the Market System' by Israel Kirzner Parts 35-36: 'Economic Justice and the Spontaneous Order' by Gerald O'Driscoll Parts 37-38: 'Theories of Interest' (incomplete) by Israel Kirzner
  - Law and Economics series, San Diego
    - W. Allen Wallis lecture: Law and the Economy, 15 January 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010500
    - Henry Manne lecture: Individual Constraints and Incentives in Government Regulation of Business, 29 January 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010501
    - James Liebler lecture: The Political Economy of Resentment, 12 February 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010502
    - Michael E. Levine lecture: The Economics and Politics of Airline Deregulations, 19 February 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010503
    - Alvin Klevorick lecture: Jury Composition--An Economic Approach, 26 February 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010504
    - Ronald Coase lecture: Adam Smith and the Wealth of Nations, 11 March 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010505
    - James Buchanan lecture: Law and the Invisible Hand, 18 March 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010506
    - Bernard Siegan lecture: Regulating the Use of Land, 22 April 1976 (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010507
    - Sam Peltzman lecture: The Effects of Regulation of New Drugs (Box 4)
      Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010508
  - Dr. Martin Larson monetary seminar (Box 4)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010511
  - F. A. Harper lecture: What We Owe Our Fellow Man (Box 4)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010512
  - Friedrich A. Hayek appearance on Meet the Press, 22 June 1975 (Box 4)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010510
  - Friedrich A. Hayek lecture: Where Are We on the Road to Serfdom?, 30 November 1974 (Box 4)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010509
    St. Louis
  - Hayek, Keynes, O'Driscoll, Hutt, Rothbard (Box 4)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010514
  - Unidentified (Box 4)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010516
  - [Cotereusia?] (Box 4)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010515
  - Hutt, Clausura, Cena, and Hayek discussions (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010521
    Part 1: 'Optimum Degree of Competition'
    Part 2: 'Information and Unemployment in the Trade Cycle'
  - Joe Salerno lecture: Supply and Demand (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010528
    Tyler - Austin lecture
  - Joe Salerno on public choice (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010523
  - Kauder and Greaves discussion: The Austrian Theory of Marginal Use (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010520
  - Kirzner and Rothbard discussion: Competition and Monopoly Theory (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010518
  - Kirzner and Yeager discussion: Miseaisan Time Preference (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010522
  - Moss and Rothbard discussion: 'Property Rights and Human Actions' and commentary, and Young and Rothbard discussion: 'Property Rights, Axiomatic Basis of Austrian Economics' (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010525
  - Moss, Kauder, Hayek, Hutt discussion: Adam Smith and Subjective Theory (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010524
  - Rothbard, Hayek, and Hutt discussion 'Axiomatic Basis' and Greaves, Kirsner, and Hutt discussion 'Bureaucracy' (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010527
  - Rothbard, Hayek, and Hutt discussion: Deflation (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010526
  - Austrian Theory of the Business Cycle by Hutt, Hayek, and Rothbard (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010517
    Unfortunately, the accessioned cassette is effectively blank. This program is unavailable.
  - Kirzner, Israel, 'Some Thoughts on Contemporary Economics,' Hutt and Hayek, 'Preguntas Respuestas' (questions and answers) (Box 5)
    Use copy reference number: 91022_a_0010519
    Unfortunately, the accessioned cassette is blank. This program is unavailable.